[Music]
from Pacifica this is democracy now I've
never gained anything from what I've
said publicly in fact I've lost
everything and I believe I was
prosecuted not for what I did but for
who I am a CIA officer
who said torture was wrong and
ineffective and went against the grain I
never tortured anybody uh but I'm
heading to prison while the torturers
and the lawyers who papered over it and
the people who deceived it and the man
who destroyed the proof of it the tapes
will never face Justice jailing The
Whistleblower former CIA agent John
kyaku speaks out just days after he was
sentenced to 30 months in prison
becoming the first CIA official to face
jail for any reason relating to the US
torture program even those who carried
it out but first we go to Egypt a state
of emergency has been declared the
defense minister is warning about the
possible collapse of the state we'll
speak with democracy Now Sherie of do
kadus and port s all that and more
coming
up welcome to democracy Now
democracynow.org the Warren peace report
I'm Amy Goodman
President Obama kicked off his second
term push for immigration reform Tuesday
with a speech in Nevada a Battleground
state whose growing Latino vote helped
him win the November
election I'm here today because the time
has come for common sense comprehensive
immigration reform the time is
now we have to deal with the 11 million
individuals who are here
illegally now we all agree that these
men and women should have to earn their
way to
citizenship but for comprehensive
immigration reform to work it must be
clear from the outset that there is a
pathway to citizenship President Obama
omitted detailed proposals from his
address instead backing the bipartisan
Senate plan that includes a path to
citizenship for a large number of the
estimated 11 million undocumented people
in the United States but also tougher
border enforcement and a system for
tracking those who overstay visas
in his remarks Obama took aim at
anti-immigrant sentiment saying foreign
Nationals are being maligned by people
who forget their own ancestral past it's
[Music]
easy sometimes for the discussion to
take on a feeling of US versus them and
when that happens a lot of folks forget
that most of us used to be
them we forget
that and it's really important for us to
remember our history
you know unless you're one of the first
Americans a Native American you came
from someplace else somebody brought you
despite embracing the bipartisan Senate
plan Obama vowed to send his own
immigration Bill to Congress if
lawmakers don't take immediate action
the senates confirmed Democratic Senator
John Kerry as President Obama's new
secretary of state replacing Hillary
Clinton the final tally was 94 in favor
and three opposed after the vote
Democrat Senators truck Schumer of New
York and Dick Durban of Illinois paid
tribute to car's Legacy we so admire the
job he has done in his past life in many
different phases we're excited that
he'll be our secretary of state and I
think for John KY The Best Is Yet To
Come his passionate pursuit of a safe
and just nation and World his deep sense
of patriotism and commitment to
America's most challenged values are
well documented well I'm sorry to losing
in the Senate as a colleague I can think
of no better person to serve as our
nation's next secretary of state the
bodies of at least 80 people have been
found in the besieged Syrian city of
Aleppo each with their hands bound and
gunshot wounds to the Head amateur video
shows the dead corpses laid out after
being collected from a bank on the river
most of the victims appear to be young
men possibly in their teens speaking to
reporters after a breaking to the UN
Security Council un Arab League Envoy
loar bahimi said both sides of the
conflict in Syria are taking part in the
country's
destruction Syria is being
destroyed you know I sometimes say of
course the parties are very angry at me
when I say that uh
objectively they are cooperating to
destroy in destroying Syria Syria is
being destroyed bit by
bit and in destroying Syria the the
region is is is is being pushed into to
a uh you know a situation that is
extremely bad and extremely important
for the entire world that is why I
believe the security Council simply
cannot uh uh you know continue to say
you know we we we are in disagreement
therefore let's wait for better times
the Obama administration's formally
signed an agreement with ner allowing a
permanent US military site in the
African country reports emerged this
week the US will build base in ner from
which to fly drones for surveillance and
potentially even missile strikes ner
borders Mali where the US is aiding a
french-led military operation in the
country's North in Mexico police have
recovered the bodies of 12 people from
inside a well in the city of Monteray
the victims were members of the band
combo Colombia and their staff who had
been abducted last week Israel's become
the first country to boycott a UN Human
Rights Council review of its record on
human rights the acting president of the
Human Rights Council convened the
session in Geneva Tuesday only to see
that no Israeli Representatives had
shown up we were to convene this
afternoon to proceed with the review of
Israel however I see that the delegation
of Israel is not in the room Israel
severed contacts with the council last
year after the body launched an
investigation of illegal settlements in
the occupied West Bank the news agency
Reuters is reporting John Brennan
President Obama's nominee to head the
CIA had detailed knowledge of the
agency's torture program while serving
there under President George W bush
official records apparently show Brennan
received regular internal CIA updates
about the progress of torture techniques
including water boarding it's unclear if
Brennan raised any objections at the
time he was made aware attorneys for
five alleged conspirators in the 9/11
attacks have asked a military judge to
allow them to spend 48 hours at the
Guantanamo Bay prison where their
clients have been held on the second day
of a pre-trial hearing Navy Commander
Walter Ruiz said the conditions of the
suspect's imprisonment should factor
into whether they're ultimately
sentenced to
death case where we've asked to put
people to death and when the government
sets out to put people to death our
Supreme Court has said standards are
this High one of those standards is her
ability to go in look at their
conditions of confinement look at how
they live
activists from across the country
gathered at the education department of
Washington Tuesday to demand Federal
action on a wave of school closures
parents students and organizers told
education secretary Arie Duncan and top
AIDs that school closings are hurting
entire communities disproportionately
those made up of low-income residents
and people of color the education
department is currently probing
complaints that school closings in six
cities DC Newark Philadelphia Detroit
New York and Chicago violate the 1964
Civil Rights Act Karen Harper Royal a
parent and activist from New Orleans
said the administration's policies are
hurting students and their neighborhoods
our communities are more than just data
our children are not data points so I
think it is time for President Obama to
re-evaluate what his Department of
Education is doing and its effect on our
communities at least one person has been
killed in a shooting and kidnapping
abort a school bus carrying children in
Alabama the gunman fatally shot the
driver before seizing a young child the
gunman is said to be holed up in a
bunker with the child hostage in
testimony Tuesday before lawmakers at
the Connecticut legislature Neil hessen
a grieving parent who lost his
six-year-old son in New Town Sandy Hook
Mass killing pleaded for a ban on
assault weapons I just hope that
everybody in this room as I said before
can support
change B banned assault weapons in high
capacity clips and
magazines and that's a step in the right
direction a Georgia man is in custody
and facing murder charges after
allegedly shooting a Cuban immigrant who
mistakenly arrived at his home due to
faulty instructions from a GPS navigator
22-year-old Rodrigo Diaz was shot and
killed after reportedly pulling into the
wrong driveway the alleged shooter a
69-year-old white man named Philip
sailor reportedly came out of his house
and fired into the air with a handgun
then shot Diaz as they were attempting
to leave a lawyer for the alleged
shooter says he was suspicious after a
recent robbery in the area and claimed
the victim had accelerated the car
towards him a state judge in Texas has
granted a last minute reprieve to a
woman who had been set for execution
51-year-old Kimberly McCarthy won the
stay on Tuesday just hours before she
was to be killed McCarthy would have
been the first woman put to death in the
US since 2010 attorneys from McCarthy
who's African-American say the mostly
white jury that convicted her was
improperly selected on the basis of race
a group of activists opposed to the
Keystone Excel oil pipeline has agreed
to settle a lawsuit with TransCanada the
company behind the project after the
firm alleged a monthlong protest
blockade cost it millions of dollars
environmentalists with a tar sand
blockade have tried to Halt the
pipeline's route through through Texas
to Gulf Coast refineries with tree sits
and other protests opponents say the
tarand pipeline would devastate the
environment and pollute communities in
its path after Trans Canada alleged
blockaders had cost them $5 million the
activist say they chose to settle in
order to protect local residents who
could have lost their homes and life
savings while the group has agreed not
to trespass on Keystone Excel property
in Texas or Oklahoma they say the fight
against the pipeline will continue
protests against the project have also
erupted in Nebraska where Governor Dave
Heineman recently approved the state
section of the pipeline route President
Obama's delayed a decision on the
pipeline until the spring after
initially putting it off until after the
November election the Boy Scouts of
America has announced it's begun
discussing an end to its longstanding
ban on gay members and leaders a
spokesperson for the group says the
103-year-old ban is currently under
review and could be reversed at a
national board meeting next week the
move comes just months after the Boy
Scouts defiantly reaffirmed its ban
after a secretive 2-year review and
those are some of the headlines this is
democracy Now democracynow.org The War
and Peace report I'm Amy Goodman and I'm
n sh Welcome to our listeners and
viewers around the country and around
the
world we begin Today's Show in Egypt
where Mass protests have continued since
they began last Friday on the
anniversary of Egypt's Revolution now
Egypt's defense minister is warning of
the potential quote collapse of the
state general Abdul fat Ali posted the
comment on a Facebook page after
military forces were deployed in three
cities along the Suez Canal where a
month-long state of emergency has been
declared in recent nights thousands have
filled the streets of port s along the
northern tip of the canal in defiance of
a nighttime curfew imposed by President
Muhammad
Mercy I'm against these decisions it
will destroy people's incomes why does
he Implement these measures here in Suz
why doesn't he take the same measures in
Cairo and Alexandria is he angry at the
residence of Suz isalia and port s of
course this is a disaster it will
devastate Suz we are against his
decisions and if he runs again as a
candidate we will not elect him again
and we will ignore
him meanwhile clashes have also erupted
in Cairo including an attack on an
upscale hotel that Drew response from
the Egyptian Special Forces more than 50
people have died in the country's
protest some of the violence was sparked
by death sentences handed down Saturday
for 21 soccer fans involved in riots
that left 74 people dead last February
protesters have also accused president
morsy of betraying the 2-year-old
Revolution all of this comes as the
value of the Egyptian currency has
plummeted to record lows causing a spike
in the prices of basic Goods like sugar
rice and cooking oil well for more we go
to Port s where people continue to
protest in defiance of a state of
emergency and we're joined by democracy
Now Sharif Abdul kadus who is in port s
Sharie tell us what's happening and
Place Port SED in Egypt for
us hi Amy it's good to be with you uh
port s is a city uh that is on the suas
canal and on the Mediterranean it's at
the mouth of the sus Canal that attaches
to the Mediterranean and it's a city
that uh has had a long history of of
resistance uh when n nationalized the Su
canal in the 50s uh and Egypt came under
attack by France Britain and Israel uh
port s was a central Target and the the
attack and the resistance against it
here is a source of local national pride
um in the collective memory of residents
here and it is that um that culture of
resistance um that that has exploded on
the streets here uh what happened uh
really on Saturday was a massacre of uh
of over 30 people uh who were outraged
by a death sentence of 21 of their local
uh football team fans soccer team fans
uh for a case uh that that's been going
on for more than a year now uh there
were many of the families uh of those
who uh of the defendants around the jail
and uh once the uh the shocking verdict
came out 21 death sentences handed down
uh you could hear the whales and screams
of people in the streets they approached
the prison uh and uh the the police open
fire um and just that first day 30
people were killed including two police
officers that death to the next day they
went out in a funeral the following day
on Sunday uh 7 more people were killed
when that funeral came under attack from
police on rooftops uh nearly all of
these people were killed with live
ammunition the death toll now uh is uh
is somewhere at 40 and this is uh part
just just a part of what's happening in
Egypt overall as you mentioned there is
a Revolt uh Egypt is is undergoing a
Revolt right now that began on the
second anniversary of its revolution
that has we've seen protests and clashes
uh in the capital in Cairo uh that are
still going on in Alexandria and Mahala
and cities across the Delta uh something
like 10
provinces are are um in Revolt right now
and the president Muhammad morsy in a
bid to uh to quell what was going on
finally uh made a speech but in that
speech a very uh with a very angry tone
a finger wagging speech uh he uh he um
in imposed uh a state of emergency for
30 days in these three cities that lie
along the SE Canal uh which are the most
restive cities right now as opposed to
Cairo kind of leading this Revolt it's
actually really in Suz is and port s
where you're seeing kind of most
resistance and he also imposed nighttime
curfew and Def of that curfew the curfew
is supposed to be from 9:00 p.m. to 6:00
a.m. thousands of people in all three of
these cities uh began marches at 8:45
p.m. uh to tell Mory that they won't
abide by this that they want to buy uh
by his governance and so he is facing a
very serious crisis of legitimacy right
now uh the police have lost control of
these cities the Army has been deployed
but uh largely is guarding uh State
institutions have to do with the canal
so uh it's a very
uh significant and pivotal moment in
Egypt Sharif can you explain what the
implications are of the Declaration of
the state of emergency and since as you
point out thousands have def defied the
order what kinds of consequences are
they likely to face what does a state of
emergency
entail well the state of emergency was
one of the most despised tools of the
Mubarak regime uh to uh suppress dissent
and it was uh feature in Egypt for 30
years from October 6th uh 1981 until
March 12th 2012 when it expired its
lifting of the state of emergency was a
principal demand of the
Revolution and uh what it does is that
it um it it essentially lifts uh from
judicial people you're allowed to
imprison people without judicial review
um and uh it gives the police WID spread
powers and uh there's also been a law
passed which allows the military to uh
arrest uh citizens gives them policing
powers and it would mean that those
citizens would be put before military
trials so this is a very just the fact
that Mori who uh before pledged never to
have another state of emergency the the
word state of emergency that which is
such a despised tool of thear regim is
now being instilled
again uh I think resonated uh very
harshly with with many people to be
honest you know the fact on the ground
is uh there has been little uh reform
whatsoever actually no reform of the
police forces since the revolution uh
over these two years this is you know a
force that has that se it citizens
enemies uh and that um and by by some
counts is engaged in more killing more
torture than before the Revolution
because now citizens uh when they are
facing abuse no longer are quiet about
it and uh take to the streets and
protest and so there's a growing battle
with this uh internal militia of
repression that is this police force
that has not been resolved in any way
whatsoever uh there has been no
accountability whatsoever for the uh
over a thousand people who have been
killed since the revolution and so this
is uh what this is an inevitable
outgrowth this kind of revolt on the
streets uh and Mory is trying to do what
M did for so many years trying to use
the police on the streets to solve his
political problems and uh right now you
know Egypt is ungovernable uh by Mory or
perhaps by you know anyone else there's
a serious crisis of legitimacy of the
government uh share do you agree with
Egypt's top military officer General
Abdul fat alisi who is saying uh that uh
Egypt could potentially collapse he's
warning of collapse of the
state I mean it's it's hard to tell
we've seen throughout these two years uh
uprisings that that come and go these
clashes that happen on the streets and
there's really no uh real solution or
political solution um the entire
political class has failed to come
together to forge path uh with consensus
to have some real change and some reform
in Egypt and so if we carry on on this
path over
problems then then you know there is
this serious threat that cities like
Port no longer recognize the legitimacy
of the government like s and cities like
KIRO and Alexandria and elsewhere that
um people not they feel completely
disenfranchised by the political process
and I'm not only talking about Mori and
the Muslim Brotherhood but but but also
Muhammad and and the three main figures
which make up the national salvation
front which is a loose
Alliance non-islamist opposition groups
they uh have performed very poorly have
really um
in a way that that is grass and seems
politically opportunistic especially
since this last crisis broke out so uh
you know the the natural response is for
people to vent their rage on the streets
uh this ongoing feud with the police so
um Shar we're going to leave it there
because your voice is breaking up a bit
though we're really thrilled we're able
to speak to you um um outside of Cairo
speaking to you in the northern coastal
city of Port SED where um a great deal
of the protest is taking place democracy
Now Sharif Abdul kadus um speaking to us
from Port SED we will link to your
article um at thenation.com this is
democracy now when we come back the only
person to go to jail around the torture
program he was The Whistleblower on
torture stay with
us for
[Music]
for
Salam by hameline here on Democracy Now
democracynow.org the Warren peace report
I'm meie Goodman with nmin SH a retired
CIA agent who blew the whistle on the
agency's bush era torture program has
been sentenced to two and a half years
in prison John kiraku becomes the first
CIA official to be jailed for any reason
relating to the torture program under a
plea deal kiraku admitted to a single
count of violating the intelligence
identities protection act by revealing
the identity of a covert officer to a
freelance reporter who did not publish
it under the plea deal prosecutors
dropped charges brought under the
Espionage Act in 2007 kiraku became the
first CIA official to publicly confirm
and detail the bush administration's use
of water boarding when he spoke to ABC's
Brian Ross at the time I I felt that
water boarding was something that we
needed to do and as time has passed and
has as September 11th has has you know
has moved farther and further back into
history um I think I've changed my mind
and I think that uh water boarding is
probably something that we shouldn't be
in the business of doing why do you say
that now because we're Americans and
we're better than that John kiryu's
supporters say he has been unfairly
targeted in the Obama administration's
Crackdown on government whistleblowers
in a statement urging President Obama to
commute kiraku sentence a group of
signatories including attorneys and
former CIA officers said quote kiraku is
an anti-torture whistleblower who spoke
out Against torture because he believed
it violated his oath to the Constitution
Please Mr President do not allow your
legacy to be one where only The
Whistleblower Goes to Jail prosecutor
Neil McBride the US attorney for the
eastern district of Virginia defended
the government's handling of the case as
the judge just said uh in court
Court today's sentence should be a
reminder to every individual who works
for the government who comes into the
possession of closely held sensitive uh
information regarding the national uh
defense or the identity of a covert
agent uh that it is critical that that
information uh remain secure and not
spill out uh into the public domain or
be shared with others who don't have uh
authorized access to it John kri who
joins us now from Washington DC spent 14
years at the CIA as an analyst and a
case officer in 2002 he led the team
that found abuaba a high ranking member
of al-Qaeda he's father of five in 2010
he published a memoir entitled The
Reluctant spy my secret life in the
cia's war on terror and we're joined by
one of John kaku's attorneys jessyn ra
act she's the Director of National
Security and human rights at the
government accountability project a
former ethics adviser to the United
States Department of Justice we reached
out to the US attorney's office for the
eastern district of Virginia but they
declined our request for an interview
John kiraku why are you going to jail
explain the plea deal you made with the
government well thanks first of all for
having me uh and giving me the
opportunity to uh to explain uh I'm
going to prison uh ostensibly for
violating the intelligence identities
protection act of 1982
uh I believe and my supporters believe
that this however was not a case about
leaking this was a case about torture
and I believe I'm going to prison
because I blew the whistle on torture
I've been a Thor in the CIA side since
that interview in 2007 in which I said
that water boarding was torture and that
it was official US government policy and
I think finally the justice department
caught up with me uh jeline Rak let me
just bring you into the conversation to
explain
what the intelligence identities
protection act is um your client John
kiraku uh it's been invoked in his case
for the first time in 27
years that's correct in fact there have
only been two convictions under the
intelligence identities protection act
which was enacted to prevent cases like
Philip AG not things like John kiraku it
was to prevent the revealing of covert
identities for profit or to Aid the
enemy in this case John confirmed the
name of a
torturer to a journalist um which makes
Neil McBride's statement all the more
hypocritical because the biggest leaker
of classified information including
sources and methods and undercover
identities has been the US government
John kyaku explain what it is that you
were trying to expose explain what you
were involved with talk about Abu zua
your involvement in the finding of him
and then the course you took uh where
your conscience took you sure in in 2002
I was the chief of counterterrorism
operations uh for the CIA in Pakistan
and my job was to try to locate Al-Qaeda
Fighters or Al-Qaeda leaders and capture
them to turn them over to uh to the
justice department and um and have them
face trial that was the original the
original idea not to have them sit in
Cuba for the next decade uh but we we
caught Abu Zeda he was shot three times
uh by Pakistani uh police as he was
trying to escape from his safe house and
um and I was the first person to uh to
have custody of him to sit with him we
spoke to each other extensively I mean
talked about everything from September
11th to poetry that he had been writing
writing to his family and and then he
was moved on to a secret prison after
that once I got back to headquarters um
I heard that um he had been subject to
to harsh techniques uh then
euphemistically called enhanced
interrogation techniques and I was asked
by uh one of the leaders in the cia's
counterterrorist center if I wanted to
be trained in the use of these
techniques I told him that I had a moral
problem with them and uh I did not want
to be involved so uh fast forward to
2007 by then
um Human Rights Watch and Amnesty
International had reported that Al-Qaeda
prisoners had been uh
tortured and ABC News called and said
that they had information that I had
tortured Abu Zeda I said that was
absolutely untrue I was the only person
who was kind to Abu Zeda and I had never
tortured anybody so uh they asked me to
go on their show and defend myself I did
did that and in the course of the
interview I said that not only was the
CIA torturing prisoners but that it was
official US government policy this was
not the result of some Rogue CIA officer
just beating up a prisoner every once in
a while this was official policy that
went all the way up to the president of
the United States and so what happened
after that uh in 2007 once you gave this
interview can you explained what
happened to you and and to your family
sure within 24 hours the CIA filed
what's called a crimes report against me
with the justice department saying that
I had revealed classified information
which was the torture program and asking
for an investigation with an eye toward
Prosecuting me the justice department
decided at the time that I had not
revealed classified information that um
the information was already in the
public domain but um immediately within
weeks uh I was audited by the IRS I've
been audited by the IRS every single
year since giving that interview in 2007
but a more important uh uh bit of
Fallout from that interview was that
every time I would write an oped every
time I would give a television interview
or give a speech at a university the CIA
would file a crimes report against me
accusing me of leaking additional
classified information each time the
justice department determined that I did
not leak any classified information in
fact I would get those Zeds and those
speeches cleared by the cia's
Publications Review Board in advance
then the CIA started harassing my wife
who at the time was a senior Cia officer
um particularly over an oped I had
written uh they accused her of leaking
classified information to me uh for the
purpose of writing the oped well I said
I had gotten the information in in the
oped from two uh UPI reports and from a
uh South American Ministry of Foreign
Affairs website uh and they would back
off but this this sort of became our
life we would be under FBI surveillance
she would be called into the cia's
office of security um I would have
trouble uh getting a security clearance
when I went to Capitol Hill it just
became this pattern of harassment so
John why didn't you
stop because I think that that torture
is something that needs to be discussed
I said this in 2007 this is something
that we should about which we shouldn't
be having a national debate and frankly
I have a First Amendment right to free
speech and uh you know writing an oped
is not against the law giving a speech
about the Arab Spring or about tortures
not against the law and I felt that that
I didn't want to be cowed I didn't want
to be frightened into silence uh by the
CIA and John kiraku you said that uh in
these instances that you've named you
were actually charged with Espionage is
that right can you talk about the
significance of the Espionage Act yes
the government initially charged me with
three counts of Espionage
um I'm it sounds silly maybe but I'm
still personally offended by these
Espionage charges which which were
dropped of course the Espionage charge
is is used as a hammer by the
administration to force people into
silence my Espionage charge is related
to a conversation that I had with a New
York Times Reporter a New York Times
Reporter approached me and said that he
was writing a story about a colleague of
mine
and would I grant him an interview I
gave him the interview I said this
colleague was a great guy the unsung
hero of the abuaba operation terrific
officer and the reporter said do you
know how I can get in touch with him and
I said no I've been out of touch with
him for a while but I think I might have
his business card so I gave the reporter
the business card now mind you this is a
CIA officer who had never ever been
undercover his business card um showed
that he was involved as a CIA contractor
and it had his personal email on it and
his cell phone number I gave the
reporter uh the business card and was
charged with two counts of Espionage I
later gave the same business card to
another journalist who was doing an
article and was charged with a third
count of Espionage what is it that you
alleg the CIA was doing for all of these
years explain the torture program that
you were trying to
expose sure there were there were
something like 10 different um
techniques that were used uh in the
cia's torture program they went from the
benign um you know uh where where an
officer would grab a prisoner by the
lapels and and give him a shake all the
way up to the really rough things that
we've heard about like water boarding or
what I think is worse uh sleep
deprivation uh or the cold cell where
they'll put a prisoner naked in a Cell
chilled to 50 or 55° and then every hour
to throw ice water on him I I actually
think those last two are worse than
water boarding um but again the these
are techniques that we have condemned
other countries uh for throughout
history the the Japanese did this during
the second World War uh the belgians did
it in in Africa uh earlier in the
century uh the Chinese and the
Vietnamese did it this is these are
techniques that we have always said were
crimes against humanity and then it was
though it was though after setember 11th
everything changed and we somehow had
license to do the same things we had
been condemning I I thought that was
wrong you know director Petraeus former
director Petraeus made a statement in
October when I agreed to take a plea to
make these other charges go away uh and
he said uh that my conviction shows that
we have to take our Oaths seriously well
I took my oath seriously my oath was to
to the constitution on my first day in
the CIA I I put my right hand up and I
swore to uphold the Constitution and to
me torture is unconstitutional and it's
something that we should not be in the
business of doing uh John kiraku I want
to play for you comments President Obama
made four years ago shortly before he
took office about whether CIA officials
involved in torture should be prosecuted
he appeared on the ABC news this week
I'm no believe that anybody is above the
law on the other hand I also have a
belief that we need to look forward as
lo as opposed to look looking backwards
uh and part of my job is to make sure
that for example at the CIA uh you've
got extraordinarily talented people who
are working very hard to keep Americans
safe uh I don't want them to suddenly
feel like they've got to spend all their
time uh we looking over their shoulders
and and lawyer so no 911 Commission with
independent power you we have not made
final decisions but my instinct is for
us to focus on how do we make sure that
moving forward uh we are doing the right
thing that was President Obama speaking
four years ago to ABC uh John kiraku
your response to what the president said
I supported uh uh the president's
response I remember that interview and
and I thought okay he's right there are
wonderful talented hardworking men and
women at the CIA who need to be
protected but at the same time it's one
thing to look forward it's another thing
to look forward just for the torture ERS
it's just not fair it's not fair to the
American people if we're going to if
we're going to make
prosecutions or or initiate prosecutions
those prosecutions can't just be against
the people who who blew the whistle on
the torture who opposed to who opposed
the torture uh you know we haven't we
haven't uh even investigated the
torturers uh as jessin said uh we
haven't um initiated any actions against
the people who conceived of the torure
torture and implemented the policy or
against the man who destroyed evidence
of the torture or against the attorneys
who used specious legal arguments to
justify the torture if we're going to
move forward let's move forward but you
can't Target one person or two people uh
who blew the whistle uh John kiraku
you've also spoken about witnessing new
Foreign Service officers being confirmed
foreign Services officers who were
previously with the CIA and participated
in Acts of torture could you EXP expl
what happened and explain its
significance yes when I was a a senior
investigator on the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee I was approached by
a journalist who said that he had
evidence that the CIA was uh misusing
its cover agreement with the state
department to place people involved in
the torture program under State
Department cover so that their names
could not be exposed in the press and if
those names were exposed in the press
the the people giving the names would be
subject to the intelligence identities
protection act
so uh again this was a violation of the
uh of the CIA State Department cover
agreement uh I sent a letter under
Senator John kery then Senator John
Ker's uh signature asking the CIA for
clarification I got a response about six
weeks later that was classified top
secret so I was not permitted to to see
the response I did not have a top secret
clearance at the time and uh a colleague
of mine told me that the letter
essentially said in very strongly worded
language to my mind my own
business we're going to go to break and
we come back we want to ask you about
President Obama's nominee to become the
next head of the CIA John Brennan
because as you talk about the
administration we're talking actually
about administrations from the Bush
Administration to the Obama
Administration Our Guest is about to go
to jail his name is John kiraku he's
about to serve two and a half years in
jail these this will be one of his last
interviews where he goes to prison we're
joined also by jelyn Rak who is one of
his attorneys stay with
us
C when
we c i
a
i somewhere
die what kind of life is this out of
sight out of mind with divis this get
your head fight betrayed and gone WR
hold on ads get they roll on like
backdam puffing C the trees cuffed on
the lawn of the White House and right
now you never heard of bodies get
blasted back tagged in taxs beef Ser
sheep eating BS of fat on the other side
we wearing bags for hats oring jump Su
seat standing back to back partying the
heat everybody we live in dead H give
them a
[Music]
bless F's like come on let's c
i by The Narcissist this is democracy
Now democracynow.org the Warr and peace
report I'm Amy Goodman with nine shik
we're going to talk about John Brennan
right now President Obama's nominee to
become the next chief of the CIA the
news agency Reuters is reporting that
Brennan had detailed information on the
agency's tour program while serving
there under President George W bush
official records apparently show Brennan
received regular internal CIA updates
about the progress of torture techniques
including water boarding it's unclear if
Brennan raised any objections at the
time he was made aware Brennan's
confirmation hearing will be February
7th in 2006 he gave an interview with
Frontline on PBS where he said it was
right for the Bush Administration to
quote take off the gloves after the 911
attacks the war or the campaign against
terrorism is going to be a long one um
and that the opposition whether it be
Al-Qaeda or whether it be Iraq doesn't
play by the marqu de Queensbury
Queensbury rules and therefore you know
the US in some areas has to take off the
gloves and I think that's entirely
appropriate I think we do have to take
off the gloves in some areas but within
bounds and at the right time and the
right way and for the right reason and
with full understanding of what the
consequences of that might be
that was John Brennan in 2006 when
President Obama was first elected in his
first term uh he wanted to uh John
Brennan to be his director of Central
Intelligence there was such an outcry in
the human rights community that John
Brenan pulled his name out now four
years later President Obama has
officially uh nominated uh John Brennan
once again to head the CIA Our Guest
John kiraku is about to go to jail was
sentenced to 30 months in prison worked
for the CIA um there while John Brennan
was there uh can you respond to what
John Brennan knew when he knew it and
the fact that President Obama wants him
to be head of the
CIA sure obviously I can't read John
Brennan's mind but I can tell you that
uh at the time that uh the torture
techniques were being implemented John
Brennan was President Bush's director of
the national counterterrorist Center uh
he was also um uh a little earlier than
that the deputy executive director and
then I believe executive director of the
CIA that's the number three ranking uh
position in the CIA so he would have had
to have been intimately involved uh in
um not necessarily in carrying out the
torture techniques but but in the policy
the torture policy uh either that or or
he had to to be brain dead uh because
you can't be in positions like that
director of the national counter
terrorist Center and executive director
of the CIA without knowing what the
cia's torture policies are now I'm
surprised frankly uh also at the fact
that there's no outrage in the human
rights Community uh now that uh Mr
Brennan's nomination has been made U
official uh there there was there was a
great hu and cry in 2009 when he was in
floated for the position of CIA director
and I'm not sure why there's a
difference between four years ago and
now John Brennan certainly hasn't
changed uh John kiraku I want to read a
comment made by the judge at your
sentencing hearing judge Leoni binkas
sentenced you to 30 months in prison
last Friday saying quote this case is
not a case about a whistleblower it's a
case about a man who betrayed a very
solemn trust and that is a trust to keep
the Integrity of his agency intact and
specifically to protect the identity of
co-workers I think 30 months is frankly
way too light because the message has to
be sent to every covert agent that when
you leave the agency you can't just
start all of a sudden revealing the
names of the people with whom you worked
the judge said John kiraku can you
comment on that statement sure when
judge brinka accepted the plea deal in
October uh she she called 30 months
months uh fair and appropriate uh I can
only think that with a courtroom packed
full of uh journalists uh on last Friday
uh she decided to seize the moment and
uh and make a statement uh that that
would be carried in the in the papers I
don't know what changed between October
and January other than the fact that she
and the prosecution had had several uh
exp parte uh Communications what that
means is the prosecutors were able to to
meet with the judge related to my case
without the defense my attorneys uh
being present so we have no idea what it
was that the prosecution told the judge
we were not allowed to defend ourselves
indeed uh judge Bika Dei denied uh 75
motions that we made uh asking for
declassification of information so that
I could present a defense in in August
of 2012 after our motions had been
denied my attorneys and I walked out of
the courtroom and my attorney said we
have no defense she won't let us say
anything she won't let us defend you and
so we were forced into plea negotiations
but again I'm not sure why the judge
changed her position between October and
January it was inexplicable explain what
that's like in the courtroom uh when
they invoke National Security that the
prosecutor can come forward and speak
privately with the judge without your
defense attorneys being there yeah I I
had never heard of such a thing before
but in August when we made our 75
motions
um we thought that the judge would block
off two days to hear the 75 in fact
there had been a conversation with the
prosecution and so she uh she blocked
off an hour to hear the 75 motions so we
knew we were in trouble and then at the
very start of the uh hearing uh the
prosecutor got up and said that he uh
was requesting a rule four conversation
I didn't know what this was my attorneys
objected and said if you don't want the
defendant to hear at least allow us to
to hear so that we can uh represent his
interests and the judge said no this is
a national security case I'm allowed an
exp parte communication with the
prosecutors so the prosecutors went up
to the bench we could hear them
Whispering they came back to their table
and the judge said all 75 motions are
denied and that was the end of it we got
up and we walked out of court and my
attorney said we have to negotiate a
plea uh J it was extremely disheartening
uh JN Rak uh I wanted to ask you about
the legal implications of this case and
how it fits into the treatment of
government whistleblowers uh under the
Obama
Administration absolutely to get to the
point you just raised with John I think
the reason judge binka changed her
opinion between October and last week is
because the government submitted a
secret statement that John was not
allowed to see that played a large role
in the sentencing hearing but neither
the public nor the defendant were
allowed to see the statement which is
very Kafkaesque but in the grander
scheme the W the prosecution of John
kiraku and the war on whistleblowers
using the heavy-handed Espionage Act by
charging people who dare to tell the
truth as being enemies of the state
sends a very chilling message and judge
brinka herself acknowledged that a
strong message had to be sent that
Secrets must be kept but apparently that
only applies to people who are trying to
reveal government abuses and illegality
because all of the people in the White
House and the CIA who ve revealed
classified information um and over
undercover identities to the makers of a
Hollywood film Zero Dark 30 have done so
with impunity and with lavish praise
wait can you say specifically what
you're talking about JN re yes
specifically the White House and the CIA
were very involved in the making of Zero
Dark 30 which pretends to be some kind
of neutral film that implies torture led
to the capture of of Osama bin Laden
which it absolutely did not in that
process a highlevel defense department
official Michael Vickers revealed the
identity of an undercover Special
Operations Command officer um but was
not held to account for that and the CIA
revealed numerous classified pieces of
information including sources and
methods so when y keep going so when the
United States talks about the sanctity
of keeping secrets and both the judge
and multiple statements by United States
officials discussed that they are the
biggest leakers of all and they do so
with impunity I wanted to talk about
another whistleblower targeted by the
Obama Administration um who has been
former National Security Agency analyst
uh he's uh Thomas Drake he worked for
the NSA for nearly seven years before
blowing the whistle uh Thomas Drake
appeared on Democracy Now last
March the critical thing that I
discovered was not just the massive
fraud waste and abuse but also the fact
that NSA had chosen to ignore a 23-year
legal regime which had been established
in 1978 called the foreign intelligence
surveillance act with the foreign
intelligence surveillance court and
which at NSA during the time that I was
not NSA but also in the military flying
on rc135s overseas during the latter
part of the Cold War it was a contrary
the one thing you did not do it was the
Prime direction of NSA it was you know
the the First Amendment at NSA which is
you do not spy on Americans and what'
you find without a
warrant I found to much to my to my
horror that they had tossed out that
legal regime that was the excuse of 911
which I was told was exit conditions now
prevailed we Canen can do anything we
opened up Pandora's Box we're going to
turn the United States of America into
the equivalent of a forign Nation for
the purpose of a of draget blanket
electronic surveillance that's former
National Security Agency analyst Thomas
Drake jine Rak is one of your clients
what happened to
him yes I represented um both Tom Drake
and John kiraku the government dropped
all 10 felony counts against Tom Drake
and he pled guilty to a minor
misdemeanor the equivalent of a parking
ticket I find it appalling that the two
men who revealed the biggest scandals of
the Bush Administration namely
warrantless wiretapping and torture are
the only two who've been criminally
prosecuted for
and not the people who secretly surveil
the communications of Americans and not
the people who were involved in the
torture program all of whom have been
conferred immunity by either the
president or by acts of
Congress John
kiraku you're now uh we are now uh the
president is President Obama did you see
a change between President Obama and his
predecessor president President Bush and
also when when you were talking about
John Brennan do you think he should head
the CIA what message do you think that
sends and what has changed in the last
four years when he withdrew his name for
consideration uh in 2010 when my book
came out I I was giving a speech in Los
Angeles and a and a woman asked me a
question um about the difference between
President Obama and President Bush and
I'll never forget the question because
it was just so crazy uh she said um can
you explain the cia's pos position on
the Jihad isation of American foreign
policy under President Obama and I
laughed and I said ma'am with all due
respect President Obama's foreign policy
is an extension of President Bush's
foreign policy if there's any difference
at all President Obama is killing more
people overseas than President Bush ever
did uh so no I I don't think there's any
difference at all between the bush
foreign policy and the Obama foreign
policy which I think really is is a is a
shame for us because there was a
wonderful opportunity to take a
different path and to reclaim our our
position as a moral leader uh in the
world so I'm disappointed in that uh
with regard to uh to John Brennan I've
known John Brennan since 1990 uh I
worked directly for John Brennan twice
uh I think that he's a terrible uh
choice to lead the uh the CIA I think
that it's time for the CIA to move
beyond the ugliness of of the post
September 11th regime and we need
someone who is going to respect the
Constitution and to not be bogged down
by a legacy of torture I think that
President Obama's appointment of John
Brennan sends the wrong message to all
Americans you worked with him directly
for him did Brennan receive regular
internal CIA updates about the progress
of torture techniques including water
boarding as Reuters is reporting I I
worked for him when he was a u uh an
analytic uh manager it was before he
really hit the big time under George
tenant but again I think that it's
impossible for him to not have gotten
these briefings for him to not have been
intimately involved in the policy by
virtue of his his senior positions some
of the senior most positions in the CIA
it's just impossible that he didn't know
what was going on John kiraku uh you'll
shortly be going to prison do you know
exactly when
uh your prison sentence will begin and
how are you preparing for this you're
the father of five children I'm the
father of five uh I don't know exactly
when this will be it'll be sometime in
the next uh four to six weeks I'll have
to report to to a prison somewhere I I
don't know where um it's frankly very
hard to prepare you have to do things
like arrange a power of attorney uh
arrange uh Child Care um
I mean there there are so many things to
do it's it's just overwhelming um my
wife thank God is is very strong and
very tough and very supportive and um
we're treating this like temporary Duty
overseas it was not unusual for me to go
overseas for for many months at a time
sometimes as long as two years at a time
two and a half years so we're treating
this like an overseas deployment uh I
can call my children uh virtually every
day uh if I'm close enough they can come
and visit me and I'm just hoping for the
best how old are your kids John I have
two uh sons from a first marriage who
were 19 and 16 and then my uh wife and I
have uh three children an 8-year-old boy
a six-year-old girl and a one-year-old
boy and what do they
understand well they they know that I've
been involved in a fight with the FBI
for the last year and I told them you
know been fighting the FBI and
unfortunately I lost and so because I
lost my punishment is I'm going to have
to uh go away for a couple of years and
I'm going to try to teach bad guys how
to get their uh High School diplomas and
when I'm all done with that I'll come
home and we'll live as a family and
everything's going to be okay again John
kir quickly before we conclude what
advice would you give to whistleblowers
now given what's happened in your case I
made mistakes uh in my case uh I would
say first go through the chain of
command which I didn't do I should have
done uh I would say if you get no
satisfaction through your chain of
command go to the Congressional
oversight committees but do not remain
silent if you see waste fraud abuse or
illegality shout it from the
rooftops Congress thank you so much for
being with us John kako spent 14 years
at the CIA as an analyst and a case
officer he's going to jail for two and a
half years